howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts so - Jim
ruts show com
that's Jim ruts show com today's guest
is Robert Kannan Ryun recent PhD
graduate of Business Administration at
the University of Pittsburgh he was out
looking for jobs and things were looking
good until the koban 19 came along when
almost all tenure-track academic jobs
were shut down he's now looking for
interesting gigs in the private sector
if you think he sounds like a guy that
could do you some good get into contact
with him I get in contact with me
welcome Robert good to have you on the
show well thanks for having me Jim yeah
this should be fun one of the things I
fairly often do is when I look through
people's resume and do my 10 hours of
research for each episode is I find
something from their past that may not
fit directly on their professional track
but might tell me something interesting
about them as a person one of the things
I pulled out if I think it was your
LinkedIn profile was way back yonder you
were a musical talent scout and music
producer tell us a little bit about that
certainly early on I was a performer in
the music industry
so I started pretty young in high school
I had some success with the band that it
was enough success that we were able to
tour around and open for folks in the
mid-atlantic region and so I got an
early exposure to that and then after
that petered off you know you know
there's only so many people in this
world who can have a permanent job in
the music industry on the performance
side and so you kind of get to realize
what your upper limit is and I saw how
incredibly difficult it would be to make
it that direction and so I got
interested in being
behind the scenes so I started
consulting for some of those acts that I
used to open for and so we went from
there basically into starting from those
two to consulting for the record studios
that I knew in the area and then I
started consulting for private
individual acts I was telling them about
business management how to properly
manage themselves I was also starting to
consult them on performance so
performance coaching to improve their
stage presence things of that nature and
one thing led to another and so I ended
up consulting for a pretty wide range of
acts across all genres I got into the
rave scene the hip-hop scene industrial
music pretty much anything you can think
of and this was in the northeastern
region from about 1997 to about five
years ago and so I got to see a lot of
really interesting things and I got to
see the good in the bad and the ugly of
the music industry let's just put it
that way yeah I've got a fair number of
friends who somehow managed to make it
as kind of barely holding on performers
for you know like 40 and 50 year careers
you get them started about the music
industry not a pretty place
let's get rolling here into the meat of
our program which are Roberts
professional work and professional views
and then later on we're gonna talk a
little bit about how it might be applied
to radical social change movements and
things of that sort first thing that
comes out of looking at your work and
things you've written and things you've
referred to is that you are a neo
Schumpeterian is that fair enough
absolutely I'm weirded Badgers pride
yeah and you know I followed some of the
links you provided me and some links I
found particularly Carlota Perez
seems to be a very articulate thinker
and scholar in this field for our
audience who are smart but not
necessarily economists tell them what a
neo Shuppet Aryan is
absolutely so the there's a mainstream
Canon in economics and in that
mainstream Canon the two most discussed
sides of that Canon are delineated by
macroeconomics and on the one side of
that Canon you have the historical
classical and neoclassical economists
right and on the other side of that
Canon you have the Keynesian and the
best way to talk about it is the people
who believe in interfering with economic
cycles and the people who don't and
there used to be debate about - about
whether there were such things as
business cycles or economic cycles or
recurring patterns in the economy that
you could interfere with to improve
things or not and but after let's say
roughly the 1980s there became a
synthesis in mainstream right and so the
idea was that you had to in some way
include the insights of both of these
camps into the mainstream now there's a
third camp
interestingly enough the Schumpeterian
camp and the Schumpeterian camp dates
back to Joseph Schumpeter
who in the 1920s through the 1950s was
one of the world's premier economists
and he was at Harvard University many
people looked at him as the greatest
rival of john maynard keynes and he had
a different perspective he came from a
historical perspective of economics he
was trained in austria and so he had
some kinship to some of the austrian
heterodoxy in economics but he wanted to
create a new mainstream position and so
a Schumpeter took a number of the
insights of historical economists
throughout the 1800s including some of
the the less popular comments of the big
names like adam smith you know they sent
stuff that was deleted you know so
basically what he did is he focused on
the the cyclical behavior of the economy
and he was putting out on his big
treatise right around the same time
that John Maynard Keynes was and Keynes
kind of stole his Thunder because at
that time governments were looking for
theories about how to intervene in the
economy and that's exactly what he was
speaking to now what trumpeter was
trying to do instead was to present an
alternative mainstream perspective where
he wanted to look at the economy from
the business perspective outward so
while all the other economists were
looking from the perspective of the
policy wonks downward you know if if
you're a Keynesian you're thinking in
terms of policy professionals who work
for the government and they have their
hand on certain levers like inflation
and unemployment and so forth and then
they're going to pull those levers right
well in the Schumpeterian perspective
Joe was looking at the business outward
and thinking about what are the levers
that businesses pull that affect the
economy right and from that perspective
he decided that it was much more
intelligent to describe the economy in
terms of creative destruction waves of
change and now big no what happened was
that this it's not like Schumpeter's
work disappeared but it wasn't taken up
by the mainstream macroeconomic
community because it didn't give them
nice little levers that they could
easily control so the way it kind of
works in policy worlds is that theories
are written to the policy person who has
the power over that issue grace and so
they looked at his theory in there like
well I'm not sure I know what to do with
that but the business people immediately
did and so ever since then shop Batarian
economics has been dominant in the
business schools but nowhere else and so
it's been worked into all the mainstream
business theories in terms of strategy
in terms of Business Economics and
business theory and it's all based on
seeing the world is a symphony of cycles
basically you have business cycles you
have no tenure cycles two-year cycles
50-year cycles various different lengths
and intervals and each one of those
cycles is determined by real
duck t'v concerns for example when you
have to build a new plant you have to
think 10 years in advance as to what
that investment is going to do for you
you have to have a very long term
horizon perspective and those sorts of
economic decisions that businesses make
are always going to be made in terms of
well what's everybody else doing what am
i doing what is everybody else doing are
we all building plants at the same time
or are we all you know being
conservative about our investments at
the same time and the argument is that
when the herd makes plans that move in
the same direction at the same time you
have cycles a and B you have a fixed
cost problem where pretty much
everything in business involves a fixed
cost investment and then a variable cost
investment and the fixed cost investment
is going to be causing you cycles
because you have to basically plan for
these big sunk costs and then you have
to plan the lifecycle of that project
right so pretty much everybody in
business thinks in terms of project
management and project life cycles and
that's why it all goes back to that
Schumpeterian perspective that makes a
lot of sense I noticed that Carlota
Perez then takes that to be a basis for
looking at large-scale you know operates
in the same general space as long term
macroeconomics and and particularly she
talks a lot about you know five main
transitions since the Industrial
Revolution and how we are probably at
the cusp of the fifth one could you tell
us a little bit about that absolutely so
let me talk about Carlota Perez a little
bit because I think she's amazing so
basically we had this state of affairs
right when she came onto the scene in
the 1980s we did a state of affairs
where there was people working in
business were thinking outwardly from
what their perspective and then people
working in macroeconomics we're still
thinking downward from their perspective
and what she did is she took she was
working with a guy named Chris Freeman
at that time and Chris Freeman at
University of Sussex was one of these
I'm pretty sure he was there was one of
these interdisciplinary guys who was
trying
break down the barriers between these
different camps and Perez came along and
she very clearly had a vision of how
industrial revolutions were the core of
the Schumpeterian economic theory what
she did is she went back and she looked
at this old work on long cycles back in
the late 1800s there was a Russian name
conned writing and chondrite Eve was
studying long cycles in world history
and what he found is what he thought was
roughly a 50/50 five-year cycle in the
global GDP and so in the global world
system he saw this this GDP cycle and so
he was doing work on this and he he made
the argument that every time there was
an Industrial Revolution there was sort
of a boom bust in terms of global output
and so at first the Industrial
Revolution is going to start at a bus
point because when you're first
producing innovations they haven't yet
caught fire they haven't yet reached
saturation so you're throwing all this
money at radical new technologies but
during that period you don't have the
financial rewards for those investments
yet right so you started a bust when
there's an industrial revolution and
then it very quickly up swings and then
over the next 25 or so years you're
going to have a sustained up boom and
then eventually you're going to hit that
saturation point where all of the
investment opportunities for that
industrial revolution have been have
been tapped and so you have diminishing
returns and then you go into a downswing
and so he made this argument and shot
butter was toying with with that
argument as well but Carlota Perez
basically said we need to go back to
this because we have fresh evidence from
the 1970s of a new industrial revolution
that followed that pattern there was a
time
we're because of the World War one and
World War two that pattern had been
disrupted and so a lot of people thought
well you know that was pre-world War one
there was this world system pattern
where there was this swing after World
War one that ended we're in a new era
we're no longer gonna have these long
cycles like chondrite had predicted but
Perez said I don't think so I think that
we had a military disruption of that
pattern and now we're back on track and
so she made the argument that we need to
go back to looking at industrial
revolutions as these periodic cycles and
the evidence was astoundingly good so
she almost seen her and Chris Freeman
actually I would say as a duo we opened
the line of inquiry into the chondrite
of cycles and they came up with a novel
explanation for it by late but they did
a review of all the research that had
been done recently on historical
economics and they came up with a new
model and that new model was a
multi-level multi-sector model that
would then be useful and forward-looking
predictions of future industrial
revolutions and the model ended up
fitting so well that even though this
was considered a heterodox theory in
recent years there's been a huge boom in
interest in this industrial revolution
pattern and so now we have right now
almost an academic gold rush of people
who are suddenly noticing how strong
that pattern is and how useful it is for
making for looking predictions for this
century and so I'm very interested in
participating in putting together an
interdisciplinary set of work designs to
forecast at least the next 50 years with
her theory is one of the base theories
for that forecasting project
what's hearth area where we are today
and what Epoque are we absolutely so so
let me first mention she's at London
School of Economics which is the same
place that David Graeber is
there's a number of really high-profile
heterodox folks at London School of
Economics so that's a top five economics
institution she's also visiting a lot of
other places Oh Tom Piketty is also
visiting there so these people know each
other you know what I mean so it's not
like she's in some sort of weird
periphery in the economics world and she
wrote a book in 2002 about financials
cycles and about an upcoming economic
crisis right so in 2002 she gave her
explanation of the industrial
revolutions and then she talked about
how there was a basically a crash period
basically you have an emergence in a
growth period and then you have a crash
and then you restore from that crash and
you go into a golden age and the
maturity period of that revolution and
so what she argued is that we were up
coming to a crash around 28 2008 2010
and she turned out to be correct
um it's kind of funny because several
different people all claim to have
predicted the financial crisis using
completely different theories right you
know you have the gold bugs thinking
that they predicted it you have certain
Canton's like Paul Krugman thinking that
he predicted it but the thing is they
didn't have deep explanations well most
of them did some did for instance one
guy I follow very closely John Jena
Coppola from Yale he nailed it he
published a paper in the 2006 analyzing
the leverage cycle and he was showing
hey we are heading into a very unusual
time when everything is getting levered
up this cannot end well yes okay so
that's a good point so that's one of
those cycles right so glad that you
brought that up because this system of
worldview involves incorporating all of
the best knowledge of cycles that we
have and that is one of those cycles
that's in real business cycle models is
leverage cycles because the argument
there is that basically there's there's
a momentum pattern
we're basically financial cycles swing
more aggressively than business cycles
do and so you always know that if you're
having a business cycle swing you're
going to be having a more exaggerated
financial cycle swing and therefore you
can predict like you said looking at
leverage where you are in that cycle so
it's interesting that a lot of these
things stack together so her model
basically said look we're going to be
facing this financial crisis and here
are all of the levels of concerns that
we have but the more important thing
that she was trying to stress is why do
you even have a leveraged cycle you know
why would you even have these sort of
monetary or economic cycles unless there
was something real underlying it that's
the argument and so she was able to give
a pretty good explanation and the her
book got a lot of attention and then the
question then becomes how did she do it
predicting everything since that point
and the argument is it's still working
very well with their Harry so there's a
certain sense that the way that we're
going to move forward in Neosho
criterion economics is to try to take
the best knowledge of what all of these
various independent economists are
working on that has a cyclical format
and then trying to unify those cycles
and to understand the relationship
between them if that makes sense
yep Andy that's a very good description
she also makes a point that in her view
we have the opportunity though not the
guarantee of entering a new golden age
could you tell us a little bit about
that absolutely so each one of these
industrial revolutions as I said has a
similar structure to it and if you've
gotten five in a row with the same
structure more or less I mean the only
exception was there were some variation
around world war one world war two which
was basically the fourth Industrial
Revolution was disrupted a little bit
but other than that barring a world war
type of scenario we're looking at a very
similar structure for the next 50 years
that doesn't mean that
can the qualitative aspects of each
Industrial Revolution are different and
so you have to update each one of these
industrial revolutions with a new
qualitative understanding of how the
industries are going to unfold and and
so forth but structurally we we can
expect pretty much the same thing and so
going into the next 50 years she's
looking at the very first thing that
we're going to experience is the digital
golden age okay so the digital
revolution began in the 1970s according
to her mom and because of that that
basically my house trying to say this
just because there's an industrial
revolution every 50 years doesn't mean
that the old one dies at exactly 50
years right so just because the
Industrial Revolution started in the
1970s surrounding the digital technology
doesn't mean that digital technology
abruptly dies you know 50 years later
what happens is that there's an overhang
and so as the digital revolution goes
into a maturity phase which is exactly
what we're expecting right now so the
digital paradigm enters a maturity phase
then there's going to be an overlap
between the upswing of the new
Industrial Revolution and the sustaining
of the current one and during that
overlap period you're going to see a
golden age of technology where you get
the benefits of both you get you get the
sustained economic productivity of the
prior plus the promise of the new
productivity right and so under this
prediction we've already been there
right that's part of the long prolonged
economic boom that we've had under the
trump administration he can't claim
credit for that right it's essentially
been caused by the ordinary progress of
technology okay so the only thing he can
do is not screw it up you know that's
the president's job is to not screw up
or deny
get in the way of the economy and so we
can debate how well he's doing about
that you know that's a separate story
but the argument is that over the next
10-15 years we should expect the digital
technology to continue to drive us
through a golden age then what will
happen is at the end of that golden age
stretch we're going to find ourselves
into a new major crisis period and so if
disciples stay as they have
traditionally we've got a good 15 years
to go before we enter the next major
crisis and that's wonderful news now
keep in mind that this model is is not
including chaotic events or we are
basically acts of God or viruses or
things like that
so when you start looking at wars when
you start looking at viruses and other
sorts of things these can interrupts the
underlying business trajectories of the
Industrial Revolution pattern these are
the kinds of things that haven't yet
been added into the model and that
doesn't mean that we can't I know it
sounds kind of funny but we can do far
far better in adding a lot of these
other things we can add political events
into the model we can add environmental
events into the model and that doesn't
necessarily mean that you're trying to
predict exactly when these sorts of
other events occur what you can do as
I'm sure you know you can predict your
risk level and you can also predict your
response and you can also prepare for a
response and so if you understand how
the ordinary economy works in terms of
sort of like the symphony of cycles then
you can be prepared to understand how
good or bad the timing is for those
things how devastating they will be also
whether or not they're a good
opportunity to restructure so one of my
claims right now is that if you look at
the Schumpeterian cycle patterns this is
a very good good
time to exploit the Kovach 19 events for
a creative destruction events - to
basically clear the path for some of
these six generation technologies now
this model may extend further back than
the first Industrial Revolution let me
just put that caveat there the point is
most people don't think there's any
value in trying to do that so we haven't
put a lot of effort into that but
usually the model starts in the 1770s
and the first Industrial Revolution
where you have not only people usually
think about the substance 1770s in terms
of political revolutions the United
States France and so forth but it was
also the revolution of steam power and
textile mills and and all the original
factories that started the coal mining
and everything that started the march
towards factories began roughly the
1770s give or take and so the first year
just a revolution was there and then
fast-forward 50 years you go to the
1820s Second Industrial Revolution you
have locomotives
railroad you have the birth of the
corporation as we understand it today
the limited liability approach and so
forth
all went through the railroad boom in
England that's sort of that whole period
if you also had modern media and things
like that like academic journals most of
them were born in that time period
things like that so the first one was
mechanical the second one started going
into chemical innovations as some of the
dominant of that period a lot of that
railroad stuff was was driven by
discovery of thermodynamics and chemical
concepts third Industrial Revolution was
the 1870s and that was a very famous
Depression period where everyone said
you have this sort of economic
depression but you have just hundreds of
inventions coming out and so everything
from the typewriter to steam ships and
an international trade and so forth the
big one that era was agricultural
innovation near the tractor and the
Reaper and all that Oh
yeah absolutely cotton gins and all that
good stuff and so you have you have that
sweet in the 1870s then in the 1920s
roughly although it came a little early
you had a new boom around automobiles
the formal oil industry that was the
fourth Industrial Revolution was roughly
around World War one so basically then
that God had sent to also radio
technology signal technology I like to
call it sort of the wave based
Industrial Revolution where everything
was driven by analog signals really and
so then you had basically this mini
Industrial Revolution that I like to add
in here that was somewhat caused by
World War one in World War two
there was a it's a slight variation from
the model you see a double dip a mini
industrial revolution around the nuclear
power phase right so basically the
reason why it's a mini revolution is
because it was a huge deal but it did we
did not allow those sorts of discoveries
to spread as far and wide a lot it was
kept under wraps and under tight
security you know when we discovered
nuclear power it didn't end up filtering
throughout the entire economy the way
that automobiles did you know so it
became sort of a mini industrial
revolution off to the side this nuclear
revolution and it was in many ways
stalled you know we're still we could
have done a lot more with it than we
have up to today and you know and I know
that if we wanted to we could have gone
down the route of France and we could
have thrown nuclear power up like it was
candy and we may well yet do that I mean
there's a right significant argument in
fact one I wrote a little mini article
on the fact that if we really wanted to
get serious about climate change the
best place to start would be to multiply
our nuclear fleet by about five x and
then augment that with about an equal
amount of wind and photovoltaic
especially small modular reactors and
the next-gen breeders right yep frankly
if you use the Chinese or the French
model
where you used standard plants knock
them up in three or four years move the
regulatory bottlenecks out of the way
they actually work now yeah even with
the current systems absolutely
absolutely there's a lot of things that
would work better if we reorganized
society not even in a drastic way but
just in an ordinary way that we would in
an industrial revolution cycle there's
usually an infrastructure wave where we
try to diffuse that technology to its
fullest extent right and it just so
happens that the only major industrial
revolution opportunity we had where we
intentionally pulled the plug on that
innovation diffusion pattern happen to
be nuclear actually I'd say it's more
complicated than that
oh absolutely it was a complex systems
interaction and that what ended up
happening was that you know popular fear
what was that movie that you know about
the meltdown or something right about
the same time as Three Mile Island and
people got all freaked out and it was
regulatory over a reaction which made
him too expensive right the real reason
that the diffusion stopped in the late
70s early 80s was that you know it sort
of multi cycles of you know mass media
and just fear-mongering led to
over-regulation which then let the costs
and timelines getting to the point where
no longer economically made any sense
and so people backed away and that
proves that the cultural side of the
equation is very important right yeah
well do that by the way so we'll come
back to that specific point because that
seems to be a clear point of the Neo
shilpa Tyrian economics that you know we
have to include all the aspects
education media bureaucracy etc when we
look at the old foldings of these cycles
yeah as an integrated system so and then
let me so I'll finish the explanation so
then the fifth paradigm came along and
roughly the 1970s and everybody knows
about Moore's Law and everybody knows
that we sort of declared ourselves in a
new world when we had micro processors
and semiconductors and so the thing is
when you go back and you look at this
pattern across these different paradigms
there's an initial therm
dynamic change basically some really
real changed in the physical economy
driven by a core technology or
technologies such as steam engines such
as nuclear powers such as information
technology where there is a dramatic
difference in terms of the cost of raw
materials and so you know that there's a
new paradigm when you have that kick off
of that beginning and then there's a
cycle of other industrial behaviors that
happen after that in a sequence and in
order so once you get that kick off of
this new technology like we did in the
digital age then you have a rush to
discover the complex goods that you can
use to deliver it you know so you
discover the microprocessor and then
there's a rush to discover the personal
computer which is the good that carries
that innovation forward then there's an
infrastructural development with you
know the internet and so forth and then
then there's the service side
development where people start hanging
various different lifestyle changes and
service changes and so forth onto that
internet you know and so if you go back
we have a similar sequence through all
these these paradigms and because that
sequence is so powerful and so
predictable we can look forward into the
next 50 years and say well we're do for
us a paradigm change we already have a
pretty good idea what those technologies
are and we're starting to see the
sequence unfold and so we can say that
right now we're in the period or we're
hunting for that that thermodynamic
change right and the leading candidate
for driving us over that hump it's
actually a two hump
you've got quantum computing and then
you've got clean energy that can
undercut natural gas as being the the
most effect cost-effective and so if we
can get to that point where we have the
energy as well as the information
innovations that drive us into a new
level of productivity then we will be in
the sixth
and then we can start talking about the
products and the infrastructures and
then eventually the services that are
going to all hang off of that in a
sequence now why would you point at
quantum computing I mean it's possible
that it could open up a very vast domain
but so far it looks like its
applications might be relatively limited
to you know certain classes of arcane
and difficult problems wouldn't the
possibility and actually they're very
rapid the current advancement up the
early parts of the slope of artificial
intelligence be a potentially stronger
argument for the basis of the six
paradigm at least not the IT side well
you know that's a very profound question
because you would say how much of
artificial intelligence is simply an
extension of the digital paradigm right
or how much of it is going to be firmly
rooted in the new paradigm and let me
just briefly interject to label the the
paradigm so the new paradigm that were
speculating it could be labeled multiple
things and there's a debate about this
Carlota Perez wants to call it the green
paradigm because she wants to focus all
attention on green growth and how the
new energy is going to produce that
however there's a counter argument to
say it should be labeled the organic
paradigm and the reason why is because
we're reaching a state where we have the
level of technology necessary to get
into complex systems in a much deeper
way than we ever did before very much
how Kevin Kelley of Wired magazine
always used to kind of forecast this
inevitable march towards these sort of
more organic like systems in society
right the argument is that you know we
were talking about these things for
decades and that's always the case the
question is when is it the new norm
right and so the argument is that over
the next 50 years we're looking at the
organic perspective and the organic
sectors the technologies that work with
organic type technologies to
overtake the digital in terms of being
the new norm of our mind frame the way
we approach science the way we approach
technology broadly and a lot of people
during the digital paradigm were annoyed
let's say people who worked in Prior
industries like say you were a chemist
or something they were like well I'm a
chemist is that not technology how come
the word tech is synonymous with digital
that's not fair it's not even true so I
know people like that who are always
kind of annoyed with that and the
counter-argument is no no we're in the
digital paradigm which means that the
high tech industries and the economy is
being led by a lot of these these these
technologies the others don't disappear
it's not that they just like chemistry
just vanishes it just says that during
that time period the center of the
cognitive shape of science is around
digital thinking and what we're looking
at is a sea change right now to shape
cognitive perspectives around science
from the organic perspective more than
the digital when you tell your organic
does that mean living or the way you
were using it sound like it could be a
synonym for you know complex systems
thinking well let's just say that in the
same sense that evolutionary theory came
out of a certain set of Sciences well
the a lot of what we're looking at over
the next 50 years is informed by the
kind of thinking that came out of
organic technologies and organic
perspectives and a lot of the technology
will directly be in those fields it'll
be in medicine it'll be in so it'll be
in biotech things of that nature so the
center of attention is shifting and if
you were go to MIT right now or to
Stanford University right now people
like Noam Chomsky are making the claim
that you're going to see more organic
type technology startups right now than
digital in those places
I heard him describing that recently
probably true at MIT I mean MIT has a
tremendous set of spin-offs and
especially bio engineering that's one of
their very
Asteria spin-offs right now which is
kind of at the intersection of the two
and so if this paradigm shift is correct
you'd expect to see hybrids like
bioengineering that's right and what
happens is during the paradigm shift
there's a process that I call a well I
stole it from Ken Wilber
basically the integral Philosopher's
transcend and include so when you enter
the organic paradigm you don't simply
kick the ladder out from underneath you
you include those things that brought
you there so the very first thing that
you're going to see is digital and
organic hybridization as the center of
action and an example of that is
bioinformatics right and so you've got
this huge bioinformatics focus and what
you were talking about in terms of
artificial intelligence this is where I
wanted to come full circle if your
branch of artificial intelligence is
based on the classic design principles
the classic digital design principles
then you're still in that paradigm if
your artificial intelligence is using
new design principles that are more
characteristic of organic type thank you
then your your RAI is now in the new
paradigm and so let me give you an
example so classic digital paradigm
design principles include such logics as
modularity okay so for a long time good
digital design was modular you know you
would basically make something
hierarchically decomposable you would
make it so that each one of these
modules could be easily broken off
separately and then rolled back together
right now that's one of those design
principles that's changing and if you
look at newer artificial intelligence it
has more of an organic perspective of
interdependence where you wouldn't be
able to so easily decompose and these
various pieces of the software and then
roll them back up together and so forth
the argument is that by admitting
inherent complexity into your software
design you're going to lose the ability
to control it like you used to in the
digital paradigm it was much easier for
the engineer to control the AI by making
it modular and and so like if you look
at some of the pioneers of artificial
intelligence like Herbert Simon and
Newell and so forth they express this
all very clearly Herbert Simon one of
the founders of artificial intelligence
described system deep composability
as an inherently important design
principle and he said you can have fully
decomposable systems which become
modular you can have partially
decomposable systems or nearly be
composable which have a lot of
interdependence and then you can have a
non decomposable systems which are so
radically under interdependent that you
can't you can't split the market part at
all and with what Simon said was that
human systems were nearly decomposable
in other words the ordinary business or
the orbit or the human organization and
that means that it had some decomposed
ability but it also had feedback loops
and systems within it which made it
difficult to fully ever control there
are certain aspects that can be
controlled in certain that cannot and
the argument was that those informal
aspects of the organization should be
allowed to evolve on their own without
full hierarchical decomposition by the
designer of the organization and the
argument is that when you go into the
organic paradigm what you're doing is
you're saying our technology is now
going to be operating in that near
decomposable framework we're going to
create artificial intelligence that we
can't fully control we can only
partially control it and we need to give
it some of the freedom to informally do
what it needs to do and then have some
faith that basically the results are
clear and coherent and that we can use
them
if that makes any sense yep absolutely
if you think about the you know machine
learning neural net revolution it has
aspects of both right the neural nets
themselves are really pretty damn opaque
to human understanding though that we're
getting a little better at it on the
other hand we are building you know how
many layers should this have you know
what kinds of layers etc so there is
some kind of still some modular thinking
but the actual details of implementation
are very much as if they were evolved
you know they're not clean and level
separated etc so I think there is
something to that there's also you know
branches of AI that are explicitly aimed
at using the human mind as a model right
that's right exactly and it's what we're
talking about is in the sixth paradigm
we're talking about a shift to using
organic systems as the model for high
tech and so that means that we're gonna
be modeling things after the human mind
which I called neural morphism basically
a big part of the sixth paradigm that
we're entering is new neural morphism
everything it's one of those general
design principles that everything works
like a brain if you want to create a
smart infrastructure right you're not
going to do it like a railroad back in
the second paradigm because those were
different design principles you're going
to do it in the six paradigm all of your
infrastructures that you're going to use
to roll out your technologies will
themselves be smart and that means
you're going to have network
infrastructures that are smart to a
certain extent and we don't fully
control them and they work more in a
brain like or neuromorphic pattern yep
makes perfect sense and of course a near
neighbor of that and again we're talking
about an organic age and this is
something that seems to fit that very
well is with our growing understanding
of genetics and genetic based
development and our ability to intervene
with technologies like CRISPR you know
we have the ability to steer biological
evolution in other species and even
ourselves if we're so inclined could
that be part of this
Organic paradigm absolutely and what you
just presented was the segue into the
cultural dimension of industrial
revolutions because if I were going to
describe the the paradigm in terms of
cultural dimensions I would call it the
transhuman paradigm because although
Humanity has been on a march towards
trans human behaviors throughout our
entire history we're getting to the
point where it's being moved to the
forefront and Kovic 19 is one of those
events that helps us to understand how
much trans human thinking is being moved
into the normal consciousness right
where we're starting to ask questions
like do we really want to live in a
world where the entire human race is
dependent on a vaccine that basically so
that's the Bill Gates kind of
perspective where we may be looking at
technologies that are universal and what
that means is that you don't have people
outside of the system and so everybody
has to buy into the man-made or
human-made excuse me
the human-made technologies and in fact
many of the people leading this or women
and and LGBTQ folks it really is
phenomenal how many people in that once
oppressed community are at the forefront
of this right but basically what they're
doing is they're they're looking at
breaking down all of the natural the
boundaries between humanity and
technology and also between humanity and
nature are all changing and what we're
looking at is a world where we're going
to ask ourselves how much do we want to
buy into this altered altered reality
and for our own good or not and the
thing is that women bought in earlier
than men did if you look at the birth
control pill that was one of those
things where it says you know this is
better living through technology and it
directly interacts with your your very
being right
but it's also something that you can
willfully choose to participate in do
you want to take hormonal therapies
right so there I'm not saying that we
didn't already do that we did but what
I'm talking about it is that becoming
the new normal throughout Society as to
whether or not how far we go interesting
now this brings me to my next point one
of the things that was really an
eye-opener for me in reading the Neo
Schumpeterian material was how central
the concept of lifestyle is to what
brings on the next epoch and essentially
gives it fuel absolutely lifestyle is
very much front and center in the
present view of the economy and in mine
as well let me give me a little quote
here and I could give you a good thing
to rip off lifestyle is a shaped demand
for new products and services and those
products and services then become the
major source of new jobs and well-being
essentially at the entry point into the
golden age so go run with that would you
absolutely so one of the ways I like to
describe this is that there's a
two-sided process going on in industrial
revolutions you have the hard tech side
of things and the hard tech side of
things is what you know if you are a
Marxist you would call that the maybe
the infrastructure or the base depending
on the classic Marxist theory the hard
tech side of things it is based on cost
and thermodynamics and you know
physicists can even get into the game of
describing how economically efficient
the economy is in terms of that you know
but when you get onto the soft side of
society you realize that a very large
percentage of the economy is socially
constructed and I'm not talking about a
radical social construction where
there's no truthiness or no reality to
it or something I'm talking about a
modest form of social construction where
we realize that it's politically and
it's contingent on people's beliefs you
know so we all have to buy into
something for it to be true and the idea
is that a very large percentage of ikana
is on that side currently we're talking
about at least 40% of the economy as
being what I would call cultural Goods
and it's actually maybe more than that
because you know as you know we talked a
little bit about game B from time to
time here one of my strong views of the
game a a tractor is that an awful lot of
what's we can think of as our material
economy is also basically culturally
driven in that one of the binding
energies of the current status quo I
would describe as status through
materialism which is kind of
hypertrophic lis gone nuts over the last
40 or 50 years so the culturally
determined part may be even bigger than
40% right right so basically um when I
make that number
unforeseen partial effects out so what
I'm saying is that you have complex
goods that have both the material
component and a cultural component and
then you would say well how much of that
economy could you parse out as being
socially constructed with with high
confidence as a versus how much of it
could you reduce to some sort of
efficiency equation and so you're right
there's a range of debate about that but
for right now I'm making the argument
that you can parse out about 40% give or
take and say we know that this amount of
it is culturally conditions in a very
strong sense and that means that most of
the demand is based around how it
updates people's beliefs the experience
economy the attention economy those
things are very much in the cultural
goods dimension because what they have
to do is you know you have a fixed
budget for how much you're willing to
spend on cultural goods and then the
attention economy divides that up into
you know basically what you're willing
to pay attention to and how important
you think those things are to your life
and so anyway the argument here is that
as time moves forward the cultural
component grows so even though we're
having a growing economy in terms of the
material side
we're consuming more natural resources
and so forth the thing is that we may be
hitting a phase where we can stop
growing on the material side we call it
dematerialization right and so people
like Carlota Perez are making the
argument that we've kind of hit a
materialization limit per person per
human you know so your your individual
material footprint so it's not even just
in terms of carbon but your overall
material consumption and the argument is
that the cultural dimension is going to
continue to grow but over the next 50
years a lot of the technical innovations
that we're going to be doing are going
to be dematerializing on the other side
and that means we're gonna have a even
bigger swing towards the cultural
dimension than ever before so we had a
really big swing that direction in the
1970s with the virtualization you know
through digital means and so forth and
the argument is that we're going to have
another swing that takes us even further
down that route no doubt about it when I
hear my people say that they're anti
growth I basically assume that they
don't understand this right in fact I
call it growth into the microcosm just
as an example I have my iPhone in my
hand cost about thousand dollars when it
was new I believe three or four years
ago and I bought it and you compare that
to what else could you get for a
thousand dollars I ran the numbers on
the current price of corn you could buy
30 bushels of corn the bushels 57 pound
so 1500 pounds of corn right yeah
imagine that out your window you know
how much energy fertilizer land etc went
into producing 1500 pounds of kernels of
corn versus this little thing made out
of glass and a little bit of copper a
little bit of silicon right and yet we
value the to about the same so there's a
you know a fine example of
dematerialization or imagine don't think
this is on the horizon soon but if we
think about this organic you know AI
meets gene twiddling suppose you could
get an injection which would add 40 IQ
points right through quitting the
chemistry in your neurons or something
and think what would you pay for that
the answer is a shitload and what would
it actually consist of you know a couple
of milliliters
liquid at most probably so there's you
know a huge amount of value that's been
very substantially deep materialized and
I think when people say that they're
anti growth they have to really reframe
that in the language you used which is
you have to dematerialization a point
that not only are we at the limits of
the material intensity of our existence
but truthfully we're probably well over
it and we might be over it by a factor
of two or three right and so if we're
going to survive on this planet
particularly if we think we can survive
with 10 billion people 10 or 11 which is
the current United Nations forecasts for
the end of this century we may have to
actually not just be static in the
materialization of our existence but we
have to you know radically reduce the
material footprint of our existence
perhaps by a factor of two as a start
yeah let me close the loop with one of
the things that you just said talking
about relating the material world to the
cultural world so basically there's
there's a relationship there you
mentioned how much would people want a
therapy that made them smarter all right
that is a transhuman innovation okay so
in the trans human world we usually talk
about there being so there's trans
therapies right there's like so you've
got some sort of deficiency or problem
and you can go right now to a hospital
we'll have an artificial limb made for
you or something of that nature but then
once you get past that level of social
acceptance of Technology you ask well
can we enhance ourselves and then you go
through that analysis and you say well
we're starting to have this big social
push where people are saying please give
me the technical power to enhance myself
and that's one of the key signs that
you're entering into a trans human era
is that you have things like
transhumanist Olympics okay that's a
real thing
by the way there's a couple of different
organizations that have started trans
human Olympics and what they're trying
to do is normalize the enhancement of
the human to compete
Olympic tests that wouldn't be possible
prior to enhances I love that I used to
have an idea called the unlimited class
Olympics where you could imagine the
sprinters being hooked up the blood
oxidization machines in the blocks right
yes you'd spent a bunch of money to make
sure that as you took off the things
smoothly slid out and your blood oxygen
levels were pumped to ridiculously high
levels let's see how fast we could make
humans actually go goddamn it right
exactly and guess what that is now
socially acceptable where that wasn't in
Prior eras and a large part of that if
you look at the comic book sector oh man
this is such I could do a whole podcast
just on this one Jim but basically if
you look at the rise of the mutants
right that after we've thrown off our
burgeois culture and our bourgeois gods
and so forth right from the Marxist
perspective we went through that
well now what okay so the next logical
progression from Nietzsche and so forth
was the ubermensch rate the superhuman
the transcendent that transcends the
natural species the Arg and there being
that the natural species was not the
best that we can be the best that we can
be is our own innovation being put back
into ourselves to better ourselves and
in the digital paradigm what you saw was
this well the normalization that
happened back in the third Industrial
Revolution but basically in the digital
paradigm it was extended further with
this whole you know cultural Renaissance
in the 1960s and 70s and there was this
big fragmentation and on the left you
had a bunch of people saying well what's
the new religion for us basically or
what's the substitute for religion right
and a lot of people got into the occult
and they are got into psychedelics got
into powers of the mind and so forth and
that helped clear the path for the
discussion of well not only are we going
to enhance our body physically like like
Superman or something
but we're also going to work with magic
powers and psychedelic powers we're
going to try to explore can we recreate
the
powers of these mutants can we all
become x-men you know and we have the
first generation in world history where
I would argue that a majority of youth
are all saying sign me up
I want magic powers and that's exactly
reflected in our mass media because if
you look at the Hollywood films seven
out of ten blockbusters in a given year
now are superheroes seven out of ten
that means that we have a mass consensus
that we all want our new gods to be us
and that we want God's to be made in our
own image these are very ordinary type
of people in their origins in many cases
except for they just happen to have
superpowers and then they have to
discover whether or not they're here or
villain and oh you have Harry Potter
right and that the magic hat and you
place the magic hat on each person's
head and then you decide which are they
Gryffindor Hufflepuff or so forth people
want magic and they want to know which
type of character they are and then
they're going to pursue technologies
which would enhance themselves towards
that direction so the argument is in the
in the enhancement world you can't be
all different kinds of things at the
same time it's sort of like taking all
the different colors of the rainbow and
then finger-painting on a paper it comes
out gray so what happens is that people
have to shape their identities in the
form of the archetypes that they've lost
value and they're going to be pursuing
those kinds of mutant powers cool very
cool that's a great transition point to
my next topic which is you wrote a paper
where you briefly laid out a framework
of meaning evangelizing meaning applying
and then you spent mostly effort on
meaning making if we're gonna go into a
world where you know we are headed
towards transhumanism or make the
principal decision not to write
presumably some of that is going to be
based on what meanings we have adhered
to us right what memes space entities
you know
you might call put a lot of religion or
culture or social norms and a lot of
that comes from meaning so could you
take us a little bit through your
theories of meaning and particularly
with your focus on meaning making and
maybe see we can tie that back to this
possible organic transhumanist epoch
that we could be entering absolutely
that was a great question I love the way
that flowed so talking about meaning
making so just so that the general
public knows this there are a couple of
major academic camps out there that are
fighting for a social science of this
that isn't radically subjective so most
people think you only have two options
that basically either you're an
Objectivist and everything is real and
everything follows a strict ontology
right a strict system of categories and
taxonomy x' or you're out here in la-la
land
where nobody understands each other and
we're all radically subjective but what
happens is that there's this what we
call weak social construction and weak
social construction is a system where
you have to work within the rules of
reality but group consensus has a really
big impact on culture and society and
there's many stable equilibria that are
possible so multiple stable realities
not infinite stable realities this is
the important point there are some right
and so what people who work within this
weak social construction camp is they
look at theories of what is this small
set of probable impossible social
realities out of the infinite muck and
one of those theories is institutional
theory and institutional theory came out
of Thorstein Veblen work and some of the
other early sociologists over a hundred
years ago and what they were talking
about is that people basically form
groups and then when they're in those
groups there's a certain level of group
reality that's only it's true in that
place in that set of relationships but
if you are external to those sets of
relationships that aspect of reality is
irrelevant so it's a localized reality
and anyone who's ever been in a company
or an organization knows that there's a
local culture right
of course it's not that nutty it's not
that hard to wrap your head around but
it's also profound because very
interesting things can happen in those
spaces and so the argument is this the
institutional theory has says that
there's certain dominant institutional
logics that's what they call it
institutional logics and what happens is
that when you're in a certain period of
human history or if you're in a certain
social organization these institutional
logics will dominate they are going to
be the ways that people make sense of
the world there and that when the
institutional logics change that the
social order changes and then people use
that new logic as the new normal okay
and one of those examples is often given
is like you know in during during
modernity people believe that basically
that capitalism was a force for good
predominantly and so any logic related
to capitalist thinking would be
normalized that's just a vague example
but it's true that's one of the examples
they like to focus on is whether or not
you have a normal sense of normal about
those things and those logics are going
to change when you go into the sixth
paradigm okay now meaning making
concerns how those new meanings are made
on the high level so on the paradigm
addict level when you're talking about
people who are going to have a big
impact on the on everybody else
those are meaning makers they're super
actors they're people who have more
power than everybody else does in terms
of shaping the beliefs of the social
system and the idea is that meaning
making is the study of the literal
process by which the new meanings are
made which then become the new normal
then those meanings structure
sense-making for everybody else and so
there's a bit of an imprinting process
and that imprinting means that the
individuals have some effect on history
the personality of Steve Jobs for
example had some effect on the company
Apple so there is an imprinting process
when super actors in society advanced
new meanings what my work does is it
talks about meanings as existing in a
belief network so the idea is that think
about society as a cloud of beliefs just
like how people like to draw the
Internet as a cloud to say it's a it's a
massive cloud of beliefs and that the
meaning makers are people who have
social position in the network that they
can then restructure not only the the
generally accepted logics but also the
network itself and the structure of that
network and how beliefs flow through it
and so forth and in my paper what I
identified was six super actors that had
the most important role in shaping
culture during a paradigm and you have
basically creators who create a lot of
those ideas but they're usually not the
same people who share them and normalize
them so you've creators then you have
curators and curators are those people
who curate and manage meanings and that
means that they manage audiences so just
like you have a podcast audience you are
a curator and you are managing the
meaning making process and you are in
some ways a super actor and so you're
bringing together various different
creators and they're allowed to
participate in meeting making by goke by
working with you and with other curators
right now you're also a creator to some
extent as well so it's not that each
individual is constrained holding one of
these roles there are some people who
play multiple roles but so anyway you
have the Creator curator relationship
and so they need each other basically
the curator has to attach those beliefs
to specific audiences and make sense of
them whereas the Creator
have to discover the new meanings and
then help to evangelize those things a
little bit so anyway there's a sequence
creators and curators are the meaning
makers and then there's a meaning
evangelizing process and during the
meaning evangelizing process these
beliefs have to be scoped out wide to
other groups to other audiences and
organizations and then there's also this
scaling up of priorities so you'll have
certain individuals who are evangelists
who will take a particular idea and
prioritize it for their group or their
affiliations and drive that up so that's
the evangelizing processes I call them
networkers and evangelists and then in
the third part I talk about signifiers
and critics and what a signifier is is
somebody who's a doer they put the
beliefs into practice rather than debate
them derive them share them they're the
ones who are epitomizing that belief and
so what happens is that once that person
does it everybody else can model their
behavior directly and imitate them and
say okay so that's how we do it an
example of a signifier for the beatnik
community was Neal Cassady where
basically you had beatniks who are
writing about being beat but then they
needed main characters who exemplified
it and put those beliefs in the practice
and so Neal Cassady was the guy who was
their their epitome of beat you know and
so he was a signifier and then you have
critics and critics are those people who
butter their bread on rejecting or
critiquing attempts to put those beliefs
into practice and they're either gonna
criticize people on failing to live up
to the theory or doing it wrong or
they're gonna criticize the theory
itself is failing and saying well we had
this theory of how the world works but
I'm rejecting it because it didn't seem
to work and so the argument is that this
is the life cycle of meaning-making
and that until you have all of these
actor types fulfilled you don't have
enough of a social movement
to exemplify a change of meaning in
society so it's a lifecycle that needs
to successfully run and uh say a
prototype phase and once you have
prototype to set of beliefs and you've
got a complete cycle of social actors
who are representing that then you can
start cloning those social movements and
repeating them again and again and
having other creators other curators and
so forth start spinning off into second
and third level activities along that
same trajectory and now you have a
social movement that makes a lot of
sense and of course I'm assuming that
you are assuming that all this happens
in a essentially Darwinian context right
I'm a medic propagation that you know
some meanings don't take right somebody
wakes up one morning with a grand theory
of everything and they tell it to their
wife and she laughs at him oh well that
was the end of that meaning-making right
I could tell you well other meanings you
go that didn't sound as crazy as I
thought it might be and then it
gradually finds two people that find it
interesting etc and then you have 10 etc
and then there's essentially a mimetic
competition that goes on until you
recruit the various functional actors
that you describe and that they can then
rebroadcast and can up regulate the
signal in our game be world right now
I'm pushing really hard for people to go
from theory to practice because until we
have those prototype exemplars it's real
easy to say it's a goddamn talk fast and
nothing more right exactly and you and I
probably both have this bias towards
prototypes I don't know but I know I do
the idea is that if if I can't see a
prototype of an idea I don't think it's
fully formed yet so there's a lot of
people who run around with idea
fragments and a large part of the
meaning economy is to try to take these
various fragments and compile them and
this is the reason why you can't simply
develop a new society through analysis
you need synthesis and you also need
experimentation right complex systems
you cannot see very far into the
unfolding of a totally new complex
system and so I've strongly focused in
on my own writing
about the need to do probes at
reasonable costs to learn from those
probes and to adapt and in fact in our
game be world the first actual
transition from individual actions and
theory we actually call a proto be right
the first form of game B that will
actually exist in the world with you
know at least dozens of people operating
together in a game B fashion we
literally call proto B because I want it
to signal that hey this is an experiment
it might go wrong also strongly suggest
that we do multiple for adobe's because
some of them will fail for all kinds of
reasons either systemic or idiosyncratic
absolutely and so there is this lovely
phenomenon where this is a beautiful set
by the way there's a lovely phenomenon
in the industrial revolution cycle that
there is a utopianist movement that
happens at the beginning of each of
these cycles and the utopianist movement
is only somewhat motivated by technology
but it's more motivated by the lifestyle
promise that the promise that there's
going to be new sustainable ways of
living and what happens is that you know
there's there's always people who are
looking well into the future and hoping
and they're looking for that that next
big thing that's going to turn the
corner so that we can have the great
society and so there's utopianist
movements and communalist living
movements that explode at the beginning
of each Industrial Revolution and
Nicholas Christakis recently wrote a
book about this called blueprint and
he's a he's a sociologist at Yale
University and one of the observations
that he made was that roughly every 50
years there's this utopian experiment
period now he didn't he didn't make the
connection that that also happened to be
the same time period of an industrial
revolution but it is the case and so
what happens is that like in the 1960s
for example there was this utopianist
uptake of new communalism and you had
everybody from one side of the spectrum
to the other on one side had like the
church of satan you know
which was an emergence of the 1960s and
then on the other side you have these
sort of like love cults you know and you
can just have everything from biker
gangs to - you know and that's exactly
what happened is there was a explosion
of you totally experiments and everybody
was doing their part to participate in
the grand social scheme even though
they're not thinking of that not all
those people who did that we're thinking
about it as or running an experiment so
that you guys can benefit from my
failures necessarily walking around
there thinking that way but as it just
so happens from a bird's eye view that's
exactly what they were doing they were
trying thousands of different variations
of the new world culturally and then
figuring out what stuck and those things
that stuck the most became normalized
and were taken up into the mainstream
and some of those things had temporary
importance they were really important
for the emergent days so for example
there was a lot of postmodern talk that
was important we had to go through that
conversation we had to talk about
postmodern relativistic thinking and
radical individual perspective and so
forth we had to go through that because
that helped loosen the gears and helped
create the social movements but a lot of
those things didn't have any longevity
they got stuck or died in the
Emergencies because they weren't
designed for the growth phase those
ideas which were well designed to scale
were those ideas which became the new
normal and were taken up during that
growth phase very much felt like there's
new corporations that are born during
these time periods and those that are
wealth like Apple Apple was fit to scale
a lot of people will tell you that that
Apple was an unfortunate compromise
because we didn't get to have all the
lovely radical things that you know
Steve Wozniak and most of the first
generation computer geeks wanted but the
difference was that his his trajectory
was scalable
he understood culture right I knew was
niak a bit
ever met jobs but a very good friend of
mine worked cheek-by-jowl jobs for 10
years so I got a fair amount of jobs
secondhand and yeah Wozniak had the
spirit of the hacker right but Jobs
understood what it took to actually
create a cultural revolution right and
the idea has to do with people who live
in the emergence phase it's like the the
Indian blind man and the elephant
parable where you're standing on
different sides of the elephant and
whatever size the elephant you're
touching you think that's what the whole
object looks like well what happens is
that if you're a part of the Cultural
Revolution you don't know what you don't
know you don't know what part of this of
the overall social movement you really
are and so wherever you're standing you
think this is the thing I mean it makes
sense to mean right it's what I like
it's what motivates me and I know it's
good and so Wozniak was one of those
people who he knew the inherent value of
open systems he knew the inherent value
of the hackable systems all of that was
very clear the Apple one and Apple two
were technically convincing right there
was nothing about it where you would say
well that was a technical failure it was
a technical success
one of my favorite parts of that success
was his invention of color using radio
frequencies basically there was no other
technology available at the time they
could do color graphics for under a
thousand dollars and he did it for a
buck because he figured out how to hack
a computer chip to make it give you the
color right and so we know he had the
technical know-how and that he could
convince other engineers this is the
direction that engineers want to go but
what he didn't understand was the rest
of society and their needs and so he was
making a computer for the 2% of people
who understood the value of having that
deep control over the system and the the
ability to build your own peripherals
and the ability to expand and all that
but what Jobs understood was that that
was a face that was a period and it was
a feeding frenzy of getting into the
that what I call the paradigm attic
level of design so what happened was
that people who got into the paradigm
attic level of design and technology in
the 1970s had wonderful careers you know
they went on they had the ability to
write their own futures they could go
around and the first gen adopters of the
Wozniak technology would go around and
be route designers and developers for
for the whole paradigm because they knew
how it worked on the route level they
understood the principles so
fundamentally that they didn't need to
guess as they were innovating forward it
all made sense to them intuitively but
what Steve Jobs basically said is well
ok that's good if you're a creator but
I'm what about if we go curator forward
and we started thinking about all the
audiences out there and what their needs
are and what they're looking for and so
forth and so what you end up finding out
is that to cross the chasm you know
everybody in the valley knows about
crossing the chasm
you got Geoffrey Moore Yeah right to
cross the chasm you have to be able to
move away from just that lead user set
of needs the lead user component and say
well what's the other side of reality
need and Jobs was one of those people
who basically had that vision by the way
one historical clarification Jobs also
had more help than probably anybody else
in history ever in developing such a
company when he was developing Apple he
spent a lot of time in conversations
with with the who's who in the valley he
was very good at doing his research and
a lot of his ideas actually came from
Intel a lot of people don't know that
but basically he did these deep work out
sessions with what's-his-name the mayor
of Silicon Valley
Robert noise noise that's who I was
thinking of so basically he stepped five
weeks in Robert noises basement
discussing the future of Apple and the
direction of the technology and the
strategy that he would have to employ
over the next 10 15 years so it's not
like he just dreamt this all up himself
what he did is he went and talked to all
of the creators and the
since makers of the digital paradigm and
he did his homework and he said well I
need to learn that logic so I can be
consistent and true to it
getting of course he also famously went
everywhere he went the Xerox PARC where
they made the mistake of showing him the
alto right which other graphic user
interface with a mouse right and he goes
aha
so yeah he was a great synthesizer no
doubt about it Oh in a book so the Dinah
book that's one of my favorite science
stories here about paradigms the Dinah
book project Alan Kay he was the first
person to do a PhD in computer science
from Utah and he got to do a radical
dissertation because it was a new field
and he did her dissertation about a
theoretical Dynabook that would be this
new computing platform and design for
the future and he knew it didn't exist
yet but his argument was this is the
future that we're innovating toward it's
the roadmap so he claimed that all
personal computing technologies would
eventually align on the roadmap to the
dynamic well just so happens that the
Dinah book is the iPad ok
it's the iPad so Steve Jobs one of his
relationships to CX part was Alan Kay
who was there at that time and it was
one of the ideas that he was exposed to
he became aware of the Dinah book and so
he wanted to see what the hell Alan Kay
was working on because he said this is
the guy who knows what he's talking
about and L&K was one of the people who
was developing the graphic user
interface for the alto and that was a
side project it wasn't the major project
of that that facility there's only a few
people who are working on that
particular project jobs requested to see
him for a reason because he believed in
the Dynabook as the future of Apple I
loved it and an entire history of Apple
he had a road map of where he was going
and from day one they were setting out
to build the Dynabook and that was their
idea of the digital paradigm and once
they achieved that they essentially
reached a mixture phase for the company
where they had
come up with a new myth a new a new
perspective or direction and Tim Cook
has floundered in that role right he
doesn't know he's an optimizer in fact
to using a language that we both use we
talk about exploration and exploitation
yeah he's pretty damn good exploiter
right he can increase those margins he
can lower the quality of customer
service just enough that people don't
really remember profit margins go up you
know
remember jobs had built a Macintosh
plant in the United States and he was
quite committed the US manufacturing
cook not interested in the slightest
because you can save 12 cents by having
it made in China right and if you
believe that you're in the mature phase
of an industry and a mature phase in a
paradigm that's exactly the right way to
run a company during the exploitation
phase of the parado manic cycle you're
gonna see CEOs all over the place
looking like Tim Cook because that's the
proof the received wisdom about how to
manage companies that are in a mature
phase there but I've done both yeah it's
absolutely true you have to figure out
if I can actually wrote a paper or
co-wrote a paper some folks at Santa Fe
Institute on this that you have to be
realistic where are you not only where
are you in your industry but what part
of the company are you in some parts of
the company need to be hyper optimizers
right yes absolutely you know to take
some of this rhetoric oh we all have to
be continuously disrupting wrong you
have to have disruption at the right
place at the right time and the right
amount let's really drill that clean
home because that's the whole theme here
of this conversation that you and I are
having is it's all about timing and this
is a timing dominant perspective of
history of strategy of organ and
organizing of markets the argument being
is that if you have a life cycle pattern
then you need to align the capabilities
with the environment at the right place
at the right time
absolutely in fact you know for instance
I am gearing up as I always do to
actually make some venture investments
during the recession the best time to
make venture investments is about twelve
months after the start of a recession
for a whole bunch of reasons right so
these cycles operate at every scale and
have different signals that are there
let's do one last thing here we're
getting near the end of our time here I
think maybe we'll tie together a lot of
the points and also give you a chance to
freelance a little bit we have your five
previous transitions the concept that
we're in the process of entering the
sixth into the organic paradigm also
carload of Perez's idea which I think
you share that lifestyle is one of the
key aspects that draws the products
services and technologies forward into
an actual new paradigm I'd like to hear
you speculate a little bit about what is
the life style of the organic epoch
gonna look like absolutely so on the
cultural side it's always much more
difficult to make firm predictions
because as you and I discussed there's a
there's a rabid competition among
cultural elements and concepts and
there's a bit of an execution issue it's
not just whether or not the idea was a
good idea but who actually executed well
socially and was able to win the battle
for prominence right and so there's
definitely a lot of that but I will
argue that if we're talking about the
emergence phase of the sixth paradigm we
have some strong contenders of who who
may be some of the strong cultural
concepts one of those is solar Punk okay
because because look before you talk
about the new normal for like 30 40
years down the road the important
question is who are the people who are
transitioning us and so Solar Punk is a
perspective that says we're going to be
makers we're going to be doers or are
going to be hackers but we're going to
be operating in the new paradigm
technologies predominantly and those are
going to be solar those are going to be
biohacking
those are going to be trying to find
ways to use
Alexa T thinking and artificial
intelligence and service type robotics
which I want to point out service type
robotics are a sixth paradigm technology
whereas the industrial type robotics
were more fifth paradigm and that
largely has to do with that
decomposability perspective that the
industrial robots have to be controled
very precisely and they tend to not go
off message as much as service robots
which needs to continually evolve and
we're looking at creating learning
robots that are going to go well beyond
what their creators intent and so the a
solar Punk is somebody who understands
that all of these technologies have
relationships to each other and that
they're looking to create a combination
of off-grid sustainable decentralized
and hackable things that are going to
bridge us into it the next paradigm I'm
also going to add into that that game B
does seem to have enough influence in
the United States that I would put it in
the list of contenders of conversations
that have been ongoing and you know you
and I may have a different perspective
about the prehistory of game B I don't
know we may but it seems as if a lot of
it was through a very steady thread
through cybernetic Theory through
Stewart Brand and the Whole Earth
Catalog basically there's been a long
precedent of cultural movements that
have a techno futurist perspective but
are on the cultural side of those right
so they know that there's an
interrelationship between technological
revolution and cultural revolution
intuitively and they're the people
trying to anticipate where those things
grow game B is one of those and I see
the game B group as being those people
who are trying to prepare for the sixth
paradigm in many ways that's my way of
taking it
one of those groups is peer-to-peer in
Europe and other parts of the world
there has been a highly decentralized
movement of highly decentralized bankers
and these are people who were part of
the cryptocurrency world and people who
are part of and actually solving
rejected cryptocurrency at the beginning
may they were like it's too capitalist
but Michele ballons is one of my friends
that's at the helm of a lot of projects
in the p2p world and these are people
who are looking at a Commons based
society and their idea of what a commons
based society is is not strictly Marxist
it's sort of what post Marxists it's
also post capitalist they like to use
that word as well and they're not really
saying that they're truly anti either
what they're saying is that there's
going to be a new synthesis of ideas
that make both of those perspectives
obsolete and that we were going to
organize herself from the bottom up from
the local level up from neighborhood
cities you know on up rather than from
the top down
there's going to be a mass desire to
exit the older systems and to under
throw those systems rather than
overthrow them and I got to give credit
to uh max borders because he's the one
who introduced me to the under throw
term I love it but basically so people
who are looking for ways to create local
new economies and societies that want to
build those concepts around cooperative
individualism big emphasis on
individuality and a deepening of the
sense of individual differences while at
the same time finding clever ways to
make the most of those human differences
in collective organization
and to use markets without a profit
focus interestingly enough I'm going to
make the argument that every single
Industrial Revolution we've started off
with an anarchist socialist movement it
just so seems that the cultural
entrepreneurs tend to think in those
terms and the argument there is that
even if they didn't it would make sense
in their self-interest that they would
want to start with small experiments and
so they would think about it in those
terms and you would create these local
experiments and then you would think
about how to scale them and so anyway
the argument is we've got several
different anarcho socialists biased
groups but these groups want to move
away from the prior institutional logics
of how and why and they want to do it
with a way that fully embraces the new
paradigm as something that's a little
bit qualitatively discontinuous and
thought from the past absolutely
so they recreate Krabat khun's you know
anarchist theory of the 1840s or
something yeah that's what I like about
these new things you know you mentioned
Mikkel bow and he's gonna be on the show
next month actually and certainly we
believe that the p2p movement which he
runs the foundation which is probably
the center of is very closely related to
our game B movement to some of these
other things being overlapped in fact
I've got a new term actually which I
stole from Bruce Kunkel one of our game
B guys yeah I know yeah great fella and
he says alignment beyond agreement that
there's a bunch of us out there moving
towards something I label it what comes
next we don't know the real details each
group has its own viewpoint about what
this might be but we all need to have
system illogical modesty about
predicting the unfolding of complex
systems but we're all generally pointed
in the same direction which I find to be
very interesting that's right and it's
mostly these are just different flavors
and the same general theme and so my
argument is when you have convergence of
agreement on what you think the dominant
themes of the future are you should you
should take note because
historically we've had a very good track
record of being correct about that you
know people say well you can't predict
the future and these these radical
innovations and I say the hell you can't
if you go back and you look in history
there always were people who had it
pretty well mailed the question is
whether or not they won the argument
during their own time and so it's hard
to necessarily know 50 years in advance
which flavor is correct but the
futurists generally agree on the
direction of these things look at Wired
magazine in the 1990s and look at now a
lot of the the savants of Wired magazine
we're describing the kinds of movements
that we are seeing now very good
watch you have a final statement let's
wrap it up well well I have a couple
different things I'd like to say so the
first one is that the project that I'm
working on I wanted to plug that again
I'm working on something that I call
integral cycle theory and I believe that
this is something that's going to be
sixth paradigm oriented basically so
it's time for us to do this thing we
need to do it and so we had complexity
science that emerged as an
interdisciplinary field around a certain
set of ideas that were core to
complexity study right well we've also
had cognitive sciences a revolution
where people did interdisciplinary work
around certain set of ideas that were
important to believe and that ended up
affecting a wide range of industries and
disciplines what I'm arguing is we're in
a period we need to do that again we
need to create another interdisciplinary
push and that push is to examine the
cycles that we see in social reality and
technical progress so that we can look
very long-term into the future first of
all but second of all because these
things are driven by networks as well
and what we didn't understand in the
earlier phases of history when we're
doing Hegelian analysis of history and
dialectic and so forth so we didn't
actually understand how these things
work
and now we very well do that social
reality is organized in networks and
those cycles are waves of innovation and
diffusion as things filter through a
network structure so you have s curves
and you know various other different
curves and so forth well the argument is
a lot of these things look a lot like
music if you're a music producer and
you're gonna lay out your tracks on a
digital audio workstation you're gonna
see dozens of loops and certain
waveforms and so forth as a music
musician that's how you would think what
I'm arguing is we can do pretty much the
same type of analysis using wave systems
the reason why is that you can some
waves mathematically speaking you don't
need to think about in dodging and you
don't need to basically have the waves
be produced by the other way it's
produced by the other way is produced
daily waves because of a mathematical
convenience of how waves work you can
just separate them in sum them and so
basically if you work with wave systems
and you work with network systems you
can start creating massive simulations
of futures you can start saying well
here's what my integral wave theory
predicts that we're going to have and
now I'm gonna go draw a picture and I'm
going to create a massive software
simulation of a city or of a country or
of a world system and I'm gonna
visualize that and then I'm going to
show you what would happen if these
waves behave differently and so we can
start doing massive simulations of the
future using wave perspective and so my
argument is we have people in various
different disciplines who are working on
little corners of this but they need to
get together work with each other and
some of the names you mentioned are
people that I'm wanting to work with so
for example michelle balance is an old
friend of mine and he's looking at peter
churchians secular cycles right now and
he's looking at how commons based
movements reappear in cycles based on
where you are in the peter church and
secular cycle and he's arguing that he
sees a commons based movement emerging
now and what I'm arguing is that we also
see anarchist socialist movements emerge
at the beginning of a techno-economic
paradigm so we've got a double
confluence of events the Turchin cycle
predicts it as well as the Carlota Perez
predicts it okay so when you have a
whole series of waveforms that are all
basically telling you the same thing at
the same time that's good news
it means we know where we are in history
so what I'm trying to do is get these
people to work with each other a little
more than they had then to put down this
whole promoting their side of the
elephant in isolation and to create an
interdisciplinary project where we try
to understand the whole elephant using
these theories that's my plug there and
then my other point I wanted to make was
that we've got a media crisis going on
and we didn't address that we didn't
have time to talk about kovat 19 and the
sense-making crisis and so forth
the sense-making crisis is predictive of
the emergence of a new paradigm this
happens every time we were having a an
authoritarian wave right before the
digital paradigm emerged we had this Red
Scare in the Communists all of the
various countries in the world were
going to authoritarian and trying to
control their media and using propaganda
in a very heavy-handed fashion in 1964
you had a free speech movement which was
the early bellwether event which then
kicked off a whole long series of
sense-making processes that brought
about the cultural side of the paradigm
and exchange we have models that predict
that's where we are now right so we have
some pretty strong models that would
base in political science and so forth
that would say here we are at a
journalism crisis that's happened before
and it's happened for the same reasons
at the same alignment as the last time
we were going on undergoing a cultural
revolution which was roughly a little
bit ahead a little bit of a leading
indicator of the technological
revolution which then followed and so
that repeat series of events has
happened five times in a row and there's
every reason to think we're exactly in
that juncture now and so we need people
like you
me and Michelle and so forth to do our
job we got to get together and take this
the the years of experience we've spent
working on all these great ideas so we
can help the public understand where we
are and where we're going to be going
and that we shouldn't be a fearful of
that and that we should be optimistic
very good on that note we will wrap it
up that's great stuff
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music